A Guide to the Hammond Family Papers 1751-1937
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Hammond Family 1751-1937
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5395-a
This collection consist of ca. 425 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift to the library from the son of Kensey Johns Hammond, Mr. Lewis M. Hammond, Charlottesville, Virginia on 31 March 1976.
Biographical/Historical Information
Kensey Johns Hammond was born in Baltimore, Maryland on June 26, 1858 to Charles Howes Hammond and Julia (Johns) Hammond. He received his B.A. degree at Hampden-Sydney College in 1878, and his M.A. at Johns Hopkins University in 1879. He entered Virginia Theological Seminary in 1879, and was ordained a deacon in June 1882. For one year he served at two small churches in Maryland, St. Mary's, Franklin, and St. Jude's, Calverton. After his ordination to the Episcopal priesthood in June 1883, he did missionary work in West Virginia for five years. From 1888 until 1913 he was the rector of Immanuel Church in Wilmington, Delaware. Hammond married Caroline Machen in 1896, by whom he had two sons, Kensey Junior and Lewis Machen. Hammond served as the rector of St. Stephen's Church, Culpeper from 1914 until his retirment in 1935. He died in Baltimore on August 2, 1937.
Scope and Content Information
The Hammond Family Papers, ca. 1751-1937, consist of 1.3 shelf feet (ca. 425 items) of correspondence, papers, and bound volumes, principally relating to Episcopal clergyman Kensey Johns Hammond, 1858-1937. The collection includes a few eighteenth and early nineteenth century letters written by Hammond's great-great grandfather and great grandfather, both named Nicholas Hammond, and a number of mid-nineteenth cnetury letters written to Hammond's mother, Julia Johns, before her marriage. All of this correspondence is personal. The remaining letters were written to Kensey Johns Hammond by relatives and friends, discussing personal and church affairs and genealogy.
The collection contains eight bound volumes of Hammond's diaries, 1879-1936. The volume for 1907-1912 was lost and apparently destroyed. In his diaries, Hammond described seminary and parish life, his reading, trips around the United States, and family affairs. He kept exact records of marriages, baptisms, parish visits, and sermons, for his various churches.
There are a few folders of family papers, including wills, family trees, and notes on genealogy. Newspaper clippings, notebooks, a scrapbook, and a commonplace book round out the collection.
The Hammond Papers would be useful to the researcher interested in the Episcopal Church in Maryland, Virginia, and Delaware, and to the genealogist.
Organization
The papers arrived at the library in rough chronological order; this rough order has been retained and perfected. Series within the papers are arranged in the following order: 1) correspondence, 2) papers, 3) souvenirs and mememtoes, 4) newspaper and magazine clippings, 5) diaries, and 6) other bound volumes.
Contents List
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1751-1817, 12 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1841-1855, 22 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1856-1873, 16 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families n.d. (ca. 1850-1870?), 50 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Kensey Johns Hammond 1877-1900, 36 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Kensey Johns Hammond 1901-1932, 68 items (Box 1)
- Genealogical Papers relating to the Dyer Family 1734(1832-1920), 7 items (Box 1)
- Genealogical Papers relating to the Hammond Family 1778-1898, 6 items (Box 1)
- Genealogical Papers relating to the Hammond Family ca. 1880-1937, 30 items (Box 1)
- Genealogical Papers relating to the Stewart Family ca. 1721(1900-1922), 15 items (Box 1)
- Papers, Notes, Lists of Kensey Johns Hammond ca. 1880-1937, ca. 35 items (Box 1)
- Newspaper and Magazine Clippings ca. 1880-1937, ca. 75 items (Box 1)
- Souvenirs, Mementoes, and Pamphlets ca. 1880-1937, ca. 40 items (Box 1)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1879-1881, 1 item (Box 2)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1881-1884, 1 item (Box 2)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1884-1886, 1 item (Box 2)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1886-1892, 1 item (Box 2)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1893-1900, 1 item (Box 2)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1901-1907, 1 item (Box 3)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1913-1916, 1 item (Box 3)
- Diary of Kensey Johns Hammond 1917-1936, 1 item (Box 3)
- Constitution and By-Laws of the Brotherhood of Immanuel Parish, Wilmington, Delaware 1892-1900, 1 item (Box 4)
- Doctrinal Notebook n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
- Commonplace Book n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
- Portfolio, 1 item (Box 4)
- Ledger, Scrapbook, and Commonplace Book ca. 1883-1913, 1 Volume